Guide to the Alison Mason Kingsbury papers, [ca. 1923]-1965.
Kingsbury, Alison Mason papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Alison Mason Kingsbury papers, [ca. 1923]-1965.
3663
Kingsbury, Alison Mason,
1.5 cubic ft.
Manuscripts, printed materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Drawings, illustrations, and paintings; charcoal landscape drawings; exhibition catalogs and reviews; bound volumes of sketches, notebooks and pamphlets. Also, "Unheralded Artist: Alison Kingsbury," Princeton University undergraduate thesis by Holly Markovitz, 2000.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Artist.
Alison Mason Kingsbury was an artist in Ithaca, N.Y. She came to Ithaca in 1926 as a student assistant to Ezra Winter, who designed the mural in the lobby of Willard Straight Hall, Cornell University. She married Morris Bishop, a noted Cornell writer and historian.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Drawings, illustrations, and paintings; charcoal landscape drawings; exhibition catalogs and reviews; bound volumes of sketches, notebooks and pamphlets. Also, "Unheralded Artist: Alison Kingsbury," Princeton University undergraduate thesis by Holly Markovitz, 2000.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Kingsbury, Alison Mason, 1898-; Markovitz, Holly.; Willard Straight Hall (Ithaca, N.Y.); Willard Straight Hall (Ithaca, N.Y.)
Subjects:
Women artists -- New York (State) -- Ithaca.; Artists.; Artists; Women artists
Places:
New York (State) -- Ithaca
Form and Genre Terms:
Drawings.; Illustrations.; Paintings.; Exhibition catalogs.; Reviews.; Sketchbooks.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
See also Alison Mason Kingsbury Gannett Clinic mural materials, #43-32-1193, Alison Jolly Papers, #8517, and Morris Bishop Papers, #14-18-641. A video of Kingsbury is availible in the Cornell Artists and Local Video Programs collection, #3867.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Papers and Family Documents
Series III. Artwork
Series IV. Photographs
Series V. VHS Tapes
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Letters to Katherine KK Chase, from Alison Mason Kingsbury and MGB, and obits (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Publicity correspondence and samples of early struggles with an uninformed community (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Letters, postcards, and pamphlets, c. 1920s-1970s (Box 12, Folder 12-13)
  - Postcards and letters, c.1980s (Box 12, Folder 14-15)
  - Letters from Alison Mason Kingsbury to her mother, 1930s-1940s (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - letters to Alison Mason Kingsbury relating to Stanton family (Box 14, Folder 7)
    12 letters (in large yellow envelope)from Stanton family members to Alison Mason Kingsbury includes one copy of a portrait of a family member
- Series II. Papers and Family Documents
  - "Emotional Eyesight: an Opinion on Art" manuscript by Alison Mason Kingsbury (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - "Those Greeks" copy (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Plate descriptions, comments, and condensed version of "Emotional Eyesight" (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
  - "Question of Taste" manuscript (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - "Question of Taste" early, unfinished manuscript, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - "Question of Taste" (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - "Question of Taste" paper bound, two parts (Box 11, Folder 8-9)
  - "A Question of Taste" letter and summary, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Essays on art and taste, c.1930s-41 and 1978 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    essay and notes
  - Art catalogues, 2009 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    AMK, Jillian Piccirilli, Documents include catalogues and newspaper cuttings
  - Alison Mason Kingsbury documents on family history (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Notes mainly related to Alison Mason Kingsbury family history (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - "Verse for Fun", AMKB, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - "Unheralded Artist: Alison Kingsbury", by Holly Markovitz, 2000 (Box 11)
  - Early writings, 1930s (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Catalogues of one man shows and group exhibitions (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Memorial service for Alison Mason Kingsbury, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    Detail of Alison Mason Kingsbury's memorial service at First Presbyterian Church, Ithaca, New York
  - 7 pages torn out from The New Yorker, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Mrs Morris Gilbert Bishop written on small brass plate (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - 2 address books (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Alison Mason Kingsbury's passport, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - A Question of Taste', 'Play', 'Figures and Legends', c. 1970s (Box 12, Folder 16-17)
  - The Ithaca Journal, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Newspaper cutting of the five Kingsbury daughters, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Bibliography of Erskine Mason (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Discharge papers, marriage certificate and two Alison Mason Kingsbury passports, 1919, 1927 and c. 1950s (Box 1, Folder 6)
    US discharge certificate (1919), Morris Bishop and Alison Mason Kingsbury's marriage certificate and two US passports for Alison Mason Kingsbury
  - Gannett Medical Clinic Lobby mural, press release (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - draft of speech by Alison Mason Kingsbury on friendship, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    speech about friendship between Morris Bishop and Vladimir and Vera Nabokov at Cornell
  - Personal Alison Mason Kingsbury documents (Box 13, Folder 2)
    several poems and letters in large white envelope
  - Memorial service contents for Alison Mason Kingsbury, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    April 23 1988, at First Presbyterian Church, Ithaca, NY
  - Appraisal of Alison Mason Kingsbury's estate, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - record book of accounts, 1929-1968 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Account books, 1930 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    Alison Mason Kingsbury to Ithaca Trust Company, as trustee
  - Alison Mason Kingsbury's oil paints in silver box (Box 3)
  - Family tree, genealogical information (Box 14)
- Series III. Artwork
  - Photographs of paintings (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Slides, negatives, and photographs of Alison Mason Kingsbury paintings, taken by Tony de Camillo (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Painting of trees and boats, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Two architectural drawings of The George House, Ithaca, 1923 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Le Piece du Fou (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Four ink drawings
  - Louis Fuertes sketch of a weasel lying down (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Gannett Medical Clinic Lobby mural (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Original chapter drawings, Henry Tabor (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Drawings for Paramount Poems and Spilt Milk (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alison Mason Kingsbury sketch book, c.1920s (Box 13, Folder 4)
    several pencil drawings, includes note to MJ from AJ
  - Sketches (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Drawings for Love Rimes of Petrarch, and Letters for Petrarch (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - DeWitt Historical Society posters (Box 14)
  - original art works by Alison Mason Kingsbury, c. 1920s (Box 14, Folder 2-4)
    pencil sketches and drawings
  - Alison Mason Kingsbury and MMK drawings (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Unframed Madagascar sketches, 1963 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Original drawings for A Renaissance Story Book, A Classical Story Book, A Romantic Story Book, and more (Box 15)
  - Photographs of original drawings (Box 15)
  - Adventures of Phunsi (Box 7-8)
  - Drawing studies (Box 4)
  - Original, mounted drawings (Box 6)
  - Original, mounted drawings (Box 9-10)
- Series IV. Photographs
  - 7 photos of the Huntington Club Cornell, 1910-13 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Alison Mason Kingsbury at 22 months, c. 1900s (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Mother and Alison Mason Kingsbury as a baby photos, c.1900s (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Katherine Bishop's 75th birthday, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - photo of Margaretta, Alison Mason Kingsbury and little Alison, c.1900s (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - photo of Alison Mason Kingsbury, 1915 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Photo of young girl, c.1900s (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - photos and letter re: class of 1936 women's reunion at Cornell, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Kingsbury and Mason photos and portraits, including Gilbert Stuart (Box 12, Folder 8)
    Includes college and early Ithaca/Cornell prints cyanotype prints
  - Alison Mason Kingsbury's Greek Photos, in album, 1951-1952 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Color photographs of Alison Mason Kingsbury paintings and scenery, from Holly Markovitz (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Alison Mason Kingsbury portrait photo, 1916 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Alison Mason Kingsbury portrait photo, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Alison Mason Kingsbury portrait photo, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Photos for 'A Question of Taste', 1973 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Betty Morey, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Baby photos of Alison Mason Kingsbury and mother, c.1900 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Reproduction from the National Gallery (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Large photo of Alison Mason Kingsbury and others (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of paintings, negatives for drawings in "A History of Cornell" (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Framed portraits of "Grandfather and Grandmother Knox" (Box 2)
  - Daguerreotype, unknown man (Box 2)
  - Three small photographs, two of children one of Alison Mason Kingsbury (Box 2)
  - Alison Mason Kingsbury and Morris Bishop's wedding photos, 1927 (Box 14)
    7 large wedding portraits
  - Alison Mason Kingsbury photos, c.1930s (Box 14, Folder 8)
    7 portrait photos of Alison Mason Kingsbury
  - 3 wedding photos of Alison Morey, 1959 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    photos in envelope, friends to Alison Mason Kingsbury
  - Portrait, undated (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Series V. VHS Tapes
  - AMKB Exhibition, V-9180-9182 (Box 16)
  - AMKB Art, V-9183-9184 (Box 16)
  - Morris Bishop Interview: Audio Only, V-9185 (Box 16)
  - Vladimir Nabokov: Patricia Desmortiers-Cineteve, V-9186 (Box 16)